Guide to the National Organization for Women Washington D.C. Chapter and Capitol Hill Chapter records, 1971 ca.-1999 MS2204
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
National Organization for Women Washington D.C. Chapter and Capitol Hill Chapter records
circa 1971-1999
1971-1983
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS2204
6 Linear Feet
The material in this collection document the efforts of two chapters the Washington D.C. Chapter and the Capitol Hill Chapter of the National Organization for Women. The material in the collection dates from ca. 1971-ca. 1999.
Collection Organization
Organized into two series: Papers and Mixed Media.
Historical or Biographical Note
The Washington, DC NOW chapter works as part of the National Organization for Women (NOW) to help all women achieve equality. NOW was founded in 1966 and as of 2007 has 550 chapters in all 50 states and the District of Columbia. The District of Columbia has a second chapter, Capitol City NOW.
NOW states its goals as working "to eliminate discrimination and harassment in the workplace, schools, the justice system, and all other sectors of society; secure abortion, birth control and reproductive rights for all women; end all forms of violence against women; eradicate racism, sexism and homophobia; and promote equality and justice in our society."
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains newsletters, correspondence, newspaper articles, reports, photographs, slides, and scanned items on a compact disc. The material covers the workings of the N.O.W. Washington D.C. Chapter and the Capitol Hill N.O.W. Chapter of the National Organization for Women and runs from 1971-99 with the bulk dates falling between ca. 1971 to ca. 1983. The newsletters are from the D.C. Chapter and run from 1971-1983, with one issue from 1999. The bulk of the material is newspaper clippings and other materials that document the work of these chapters. The newsletters include the Washington Area Women's Center newsletter titled "In Our Own Write," as well as "The Washington Equal Times," and "The National N.O.W. Times."
This collection was donated by the D.C. Chapter in 2007.
Most of the materials arrived loose and have been organized and foldered by Special Collections Research Center staff. The material listed in this guide is processed and available for use, but there is additional material in the collection that is minimally processed and may not be available for research. Please contact Special Collections for more information.
Acquisition Information
Donated in 2007.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Related Materials
Nancy Sahli gay rights, Capitol Hill N.O.W, and related Washingtoniana papers (MS2386) https://searcharchives.library.gwu.edu/repositories/2/resources/842
Washington (D.C.); Women's rights; Abortion; Scrapbooks; Pro-choice movement; Women -- History; Feminists; Capitol Hill (Washington, D.C.); National Organization for Women; National Organization for Women. Washington, D.C. Chapter
- Newsletters, articles, and correspondence, 1971-1999; 1971-1983; Series 1; 4 Linear Feet
  Arrangement
  Newsletters are arranged chronologically. Clippings and other subject files are arranged by topic.
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes newsletters, flyers, pamphlets, correspondence, newspaper articles, reports, and photographs. The newsletters are from the D.C. Chapter from 1971-1983, with one issue from 1999. Newsletters also include the Washington Area Women's Center newsletter "In Our Own Write," as well as "The Washington Equal Times," and "The National N.O.W. Times." Clippings files and subject files include material on reproductive rights, sex-based discrimination, affirmative action, the Equal Rights Amendment, and domestic violence, among other topics. Because much of this material was not originally foldered, folder titles were generated by Special Collections staff.
  National Organization for Women; National Organization for Women. Washington, D.C. Chapter
  - Newsletter: The Vocal Majority, 1971 February-1972 January; Series 1 Box 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Newsletter: The Vocal Majority, 1972 February-July; Series 1 Box 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Newsletter: The Vocal Majority, 1972 August-1973 July; Series 1 Box 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Newsletter: The Vocal Majority, 1973 August-1974 March; Series 1 Box 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Newsletter: The Vocal Majority, 1974 April-1976 December; Series 1 Box 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Newsletter: Do it N.O.W., 1976 September-December; Series 1 Box 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings: Reproductive Rights, 1980; Series 1 Box 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Newsletters, Flyers, Pamphlets: Reproductive Rights, Affirmative Action, Equal Rights Amendment, Domestic Partnership Benefits, 1975-1990; Series 1 Box 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clippings: Sex-Based Discrimination, Women in Combat, 1970-1981; Series 1 Box 2 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Newsletters, Correspondence: Reproductive Rights, Gay and Lesbian Rights, Equal Opportunity Employment, 1978-1982; Series 1 Box 2 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Clippings: Reproductive Rights, Hiring Discrimination, 1977-1983; Series 1 Box 2 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Newsletters, Correspondence, Reports: Reproductive Rights, Sex-Based Salary Discrimination in the U.S. Senate, 1975-1982; Series 1 Box 2 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Clippings: Equal Rights Amendment, Reproductive Rights, 1978-1983; Series 1 Box 2 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Newsletters, Correspondence, Hearing Statements: Equal Rights Amendment, Equal Opportunity Employment, 1976-1980; Series 1 Box 2 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Clippings: Equal Pay, Hiring Discrimination, 1980-1983; Series 1 Box 2 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Newsletters, Correspondence, Hearing Statements: Equal Rights Amendment March on Washington, Capitol Hill N.O.W. Chapter Budget Hearings, Title IX, 1977-1982; Series 1 Box 2 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Newsletter: National N.O.W. Times, 1978 March-1979 November; Series 1 Box 2 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Newsletter: In Our Own Write, 1980 June-1983 February; Series 1 Box 3 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Clippings: Domestic Labor, Child Care, Violence Against Women, 1978-1982; Series 1 Box 3 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Newsletters, Hearing Statements: Women's Legal Defense Fund Newsletter, Domestic Violence, Sexual Assault, 1980-1982; Series 1 Box 3 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Clippings: Equal Rights Amendment, Women in the Combat, 1975-1981; Series 1 Box 3 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Newsletters: Equal Rights Amendment, 1978-1981; Series 1 Box 3 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Newsletter: The Washington Equal Times, 1978 March-December; Series 1 Box 4 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Newsletter: The Washington Equal Times, 1979 January-December; Series 1 Box 4 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Newsletter: The Washington Equal Times, 1980 January-December; Series 1 Box 6 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - John Bennett Papers: Correspondence, Newsletters, New York Chapter Materials, 1970-1979; Series 1 Box 6 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Lucy Komisar Papers: Correspondence, Memoranda, 1970-1971; Series 1 Box 6 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Equal Opportunity Employment Literature Kit, 1968; Series 1 Box 6 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - New York Chapter Materials: Correspondence, Newsletters, Meeting Minutes, 1970-1978; Series 1 Box 6 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Capitol Hill N.O.W. Chapter Membership News, 1976-1978; Series 1 Box 6 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - March on Washington for the Equal Rights Amendment, 1978 July; Series 1 Box 6 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Elections: Correspondence, Flyers, Newsletters, 1977-1979; Series 1 Box 6 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Federally Employed Women: Informational Materials, Correspondence, Financial Documents, 1971-1972; Series 1 Box 6 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Capitol Hill N.O.W. Chapter Correspondence, Membership, Flyers, 1975-1978; Series 1 Box 6 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Newsletter: Capitol City News, 1999 December; Series 1 Box 6 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Slides, 1970-1996; Series 2; 2 Linear Feet
  Arrangement note
  Arranged chronologically by event date.
  Scope and Content note
  This series includes slides of N.O.W. events from 1973 to 1996, and scanned items on a CD.
  National Organization for Women. Washington, D.C. Chapter; National Organization for Women
  - Women's Fair, 1973 August 25; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Bethune Statue Dedication, 1974 July; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Minority Issues Conference, 1975 May; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Day of Outrage, 1975 May 11; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder data_value_missing_c4f72af234bf817a5c856d3995c50127)
  - Capital Hill NOW picnic, 1975; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Risher fundraiser, 1976 August 14; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Women's Fair, 1976 August; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Lammas party, 1976; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Erin Pizzey lecture and Film, 1977 March 16; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Anti-Califano demonstration, 1977 March 16; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - "Women to Women: Building a Community" conference, 1977 April 16; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Market day, 1977 May 1; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Equal Rights Amendment march, 1977 July 9; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Equal Rights Amendment picnic, 1977 July 24; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Latin Heritage Day, 1977 August; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - LERN Rally in Richmond, Virginia, 1978 January 22; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Midatlantic regional conference, 1978 April 1-2; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Chicago Equal Rights Amendment demonstration, 1978 April 29; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Equal Rights Amendment extension march, 1978 July 9; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Swimathon, 1978 August 27-28; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - "Must Do" Day - Equal Rights Amendment pro ratification extension, 1978 September 26; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Recission vote images outside Capitol Building, 1978 October 6; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Capital Hill NOW booth and various images at NOW national conference, 1978 October 6-9; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - National NOW conference and Supreme Court vigil, 1978 October; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - District of Columbia state meeting, 1979 August 16; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Nell Carlson's installation, 1979 September 23; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Gay rights march, 1979 October 14; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Sonia Johnson demonstration in Sterling Park, Virginia, 1979 November 17; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Sonia Johnson demonstration in Oakton, Virginia, 1979 December 1; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Pro choice vigil at Supreme Court, 1980 April 21; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Chicago Equal Rights Amendment rally, 1980 May 10; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Joint picnic between Capital Hill NOW and DC NOW, 1980 June; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Anti-porn rally, 1980 August 2; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Equality Day action ("RNC Chain Action"), 1980 August 26; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Equal Rights Amendment talk, 1980 October; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Women's Pentagon action, 1980 November; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Various inauguration day activities, 1981 January 20; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Party for Jean Lentz, 1981 March 1; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Women's Pentagon action, 1981 May; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Solidarity Day, 1981 September 9; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - National NOW conference, 1981 October 10; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - White House Vigilance, 1981 October 11; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Equal Rights Amendment countdown rally, 1981 October 12; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Congressional Union White House action, 1981 November 12; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Slingo church rally, 1981 November 29; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Women's Pentagon action, 1981 November; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Congressional Union White House rally, 1982 February 15; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Picket at Mormon temple in Kensington, Maryland, 1982 April 4; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Committee on Human Rights Chuck's reception, 1982 May 26; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - National Archives action, 1982 June 30; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - National Archives Action, 1982 July 1; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Anti-draft rally, 1982 July 7; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - S.L.A.W. action, 1983 January 21; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Crawford fundraiser, 1983 April 2; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Committee of Human Rights office, 1983 April; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Women's Equality Day march, 1983 August 26; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Suffrage White House action, 1983 August 26; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Martin Luther King memorial march and rally, 1983 August 27; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Victor Party, 1984 March; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Religious Coalition for Abortion Rights march for women's lives, 1986 March 8; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Hands Across America event, 1986 May 25; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Party for Cornelia Suhler, 1989 July; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Old Activists Nite, 1991 November 30; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Moran Meeting, 1994 August 6; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Business and Professional Women's Foundation theatre party, 1994 August 9; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Business and Professional Women's Foundation national convention, 1996 August; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - ABPW at Moran meeting, 1996 September; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Compact Disc: Capitol Hill N.O.W. Scans, 1970-1982; Series 2 Box 5 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    General note
    Compact disc that includes the following folders: 1. "KALINOSKI CHNOW MEMORIES": scanned Captiol Hill N.O.W. Materials, 1970-1981 2. "NOW Archives Outside Schlesinger Library": finding aid to the Janet Pierce N.O.W. collection 3. "WET ONLY": scanned copies of the Washington Equal Times, 1978-1982